Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin American presidential collection, 1860-2009.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen American presidential collection
- Series II. Other U.S. presidents
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As Vice President Addressee: Robert K. Pepper - News Editor, Fort Meyers News Press Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 5/14/57; Pages: 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Discusses how to handle Russia. See Lyndon Johnson letter of 7/22/57, also written to Mr. Pepper.
    Rudin # P-127
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As candidate for Governor of California Addressee: Congressman Bob Wilson Writer's location:, 5/14/62; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Proper governance demands "political leaders of absolute probity and judgement".
    Rudin # P-128
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As Lawyer Addressee: Jimmy Bottoms Writer's location: New York, NY, 2/3/64; Pages: 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Discusses the office of the Vice Presidency.
    Rudin # P-129
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As President? Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1/20/69 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Inauguration Envelope.
    Rudin # P-130
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As President Addressee: Senator Jennings Randolph Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 4/11/70; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Regarding Carswell appointment to the Supreme Court.
    Rudin # P-131
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As President Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Official printed ticket to impeachment.
    Rudin # P-132
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As President Addressee: Congressman Albert H. Quie Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 2/20/74; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Regarding resigning the Presidency.
    Rudin # P-133
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As Presidential candidate Writer's location:, 8/9/74; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Announcing Nixon's resignation and Ford's ascension to office.
    Rudin # P-134
  - Nixon, Richard, 8/9/74; Newspaper (Box 13, Folder 7)
    The New York Times coverage of Nixon's resignation.
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As ex-President Writer's location: New York, NY, 1985
    "No More Vietnams". Signed copy. Arbor House, New York. Also included is an unsigned copy. See separated material below.
    Rudin # P-135
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Lee Edwards Writer's location: New York, NY, 2/22/85; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Review the American role in Vietnam.
    Rudin # P-136
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Senator Paul Simon Writer's location: New York, NY, 8/16/85; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Regarding exchange programs with Russia.
    Rudin # P-137
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: No elective office held Addressee: Patrick J. Hillings Writer's location: New York City, 1/26/88; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Contains commentary about the media and "beating them".
  - Nixon, Richard Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan Writer's location: Woodcliff Lake, NJ, 8/16/90; Pages: 2 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Discusses race relations.
    Rudin # P-138
  - Nixon, Richard, 4/23/94; Newspaper (Box 13, Folder 10)
    New York Times coverage of Nixon's death.
  - Obama, Barack, Stamps (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Commemorative envelopes with 42-cent stamps, foreign stamps, inaugural covers, and note cards with stamps.
  - Obama, Barack Office held: Addressee: Writer's location: "Crown Publishers New York, NY", 2006
    "The Audacity of Hope". See separated material below.
    Rudin # P-138A
  - Obama, Barack, 2009; Newspaper (Box 11)
    The New York Times special publication of inaugurations, from Washington to Obama.
    Rudin # N-16
  - Obama, Barack, 2008-2009; Newspapers (Box 20)
    Four newspapers/magazines on the election and inauguration.
  - Obama, Barack, 11/5/08 (Box 21)
    Press plate announcing Obama's win.
  - Pierce, Franklin Office held: As Congressman Addressee: Pierce's Father Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1835-12-23; Pages: 3 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Concerning his attention to religious service, public and private. Pierce's letter is a continuation of a letter written by his brother, also to their father.
    Rudin # P-139
  - Pierce, Franklin Office held: As Brigadier General Addressee: Endorses letter of Lt. Col. Joshua Howard Writer's location: Chapultepec, Mexico, 1847-09-26; Pages: 3 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Howard's letter recommends promotions and Certificates of Merit for bravery following the Battle of Churubusco and Chapultepec.
    Rudin # P-140
  - Pierce, Franklin Office held: As President Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1856-06-02; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Proclamation concerning the boundary between the United States and Mexico.
    Rudin # P-141
  - Polk, James Office held: As President Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1848-12-26; Pages: 1, framed (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Orders that the battle flags captured during the Mexican War be deposited at West Point.
    Rudin # P-142
  - Reagan, Ronald, Stamps (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Commemorative envelopes and stamps.
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: Probably as Governor of California Addressee: Tom Reed, Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Thinks U.S. foreign policy should be "a little hard nosed".
    Rudin # P-143
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As Governor of California Addressee: Sgt. Ernie A. Siegrist Writer's location: Sacramento, CA, 6/28/67; Pages: 2 1/2 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Response to an angry serviceman in Vietnam.
    Rudin # P-144
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As Governor of California Addressee: George F. Barrett Writer's location: Sacramento, CA, 10/13/67; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Returns a campaign contribution.
    Rudin # P-145
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As Governor of California Addressee: Mike Fitchett Writer's location: Sacramento, CA, 8/5/69; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Comments on the reform of the Electoral College.
    Rudin # P-146
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As Governor of California Addressee: Mrs. Donald S. Bolton Writer's location: Sacramento, CA, 1/4/71; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Discusses tax relief.
    Rudin # P-147
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As ex-Governor of California Addressee: Lloyd E. Rohrke Writer's location: Los Angeles, CA, 6/9/75; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Has soured on being a legislator. "anyway it's not for me."
    Rudin # P-148
  - Reagan, Ronald Office held: As ex-President Addressee: The Honorable and Mrs. James Brady Writer's location: (Likely California), 11/24/93; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Congratulations on the passage of the Brady Bill.
    Rudin # P-149
  - Roosevelt, Franklin, Stamps (Box 6, Folder 26)
    Commemorative envelopes and stamps
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: No public office held Addressee: Mrs. Teresa Graham Writer's location: Hyde Park, NY, 12/4/24; Pages: 2 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Outlines his plan for strengthening the Democratic Party.
    Rudin # P-150
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As Governor of New York Addressee: Mrs. C.F. Wertz Writer's location: Albany, NY, 2/3/30; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    The definition of ideal citizenship.
    Rudin # P-151
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As Governor of New York Addressee: Mr. H.S. Wellman Writer's location: Albany, NY, 1/14/31; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    Regarding the Patients Aid Fund at the Georgia Warm Springs Foundation. From the Dr. Joseph Plaud Collection.
    Rudin # P-152
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As Governor of New York Addressee: Walter L. Bennett Writer's location: Albany, NY, 2/15/32; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    Response to a detractor.
    Rudin # P-152A
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As Governor of New York Addressee: Lewis A. Lincoln Writer's location: Albany, NY, 2/19/32; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    I am a Democrat "by conviction".
    Rudin # P-153
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As Governor of New York Addressee: Mr. W.F. Bussell Writer's location: Albany, NY, 2/26/32; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Regarding the Square Deal, Democratic Principles, and the suffering American people.
    Rudin # P-154
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: President, 3/4/33 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Program for the Inaugural Ceremonies.
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: "George Creel, Colliers Magazine" Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 9/19/35; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    An early trial balloon in FDR's battle against the Supreme Court. See also FDR letter of 12/18/36.
    Rudin # P-155
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: Basil O'Connor Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 11/16/36; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "The national fight against Infantile Paralysis cannot cease. It must go on!"
    Rudin # P-156
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: "Samuel I. Rosenman, Roosevelt's Speech Writer" Writer's location: On U.S.S. Indianapolis, 12/10/36; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    FDR misses Rosenman's speech writing expertise.
    Rudin # P-157
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: Basil O'Connor Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 12/18/36; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Prepares to manipulate the press. See also FDR letter of 9/19/35.
    Rudin # P-158
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: "Norman Thomas, Socialist Party Leader" Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 12/25/37; Pages: 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Regarding the export of arms to Spain during the Spanish Civil War.
    Rudin # P-159
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: William S. Paley, President, Columbia Broadcasting System Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 4/22/38; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    FDR praises Paley for keeping the radio airwaves open for public and political discussions.
    Rudin # P-160
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: Heads of All Departments and Independent Establishments Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 9/3/41; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Directive relating to the employment of negroes in the Federal Civil Service.
    Rudin # P-160A
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: Martin C. Sweeney Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 10/19/43; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    FDR sends sly thanks for a gift of liquor.
    Rudin # P-161
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As President Addressee: Dr. Harry L. Hopkins Writer's location: Warm Springs, GA, 12/8/44; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    FDR pokes fun at Thomas Dewey's mustache. From the Dr. Joseph Plaud Collection.
    Rudin # P-162
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Office held: As deceased President Writer's location:, 4/13/45; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Official naval teletype announcing death of FDR.
    Rudin # P-164
  - Roosevelt, Franklin, 1845; Newspaper (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Philadelphia Inquirer coverage of Roosevelt's death and Truman's oath.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, Stamps (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Commemorative stamps and envelopes.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As President Addressee: "Honorable Morris K. Jessup, President, Chamber of Commerce State of New York" Writer's location: "Executive Mansion Washington, D.C.", 10/15/01; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Declines to speak at the Chamber of Commerce "until my message goes before Congress".
    Rudin # P-165
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As ex-President Addressee: "Mr. O.K. Davis, New York Times" Writer's location: """The Outlook"" New York, NY", 5/31/11; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    "No situation could arise which would make it possible for me to accept a nomination next year". See also letter of 12/14/1911 - from the Forbes Collection - Part 6.
    Rudin # P-166
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As ex-President Writer's location: New York, NY, 10/10/11; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Made out to Harvard Alumni Association.
    Rudin # P-167
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As ex-President Addressee: J.M. Hummel Writer's location: """The Outlook"" New York, NY", 12/14/11; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    "I do not want to be nominated for any office". See also letter of 5/31/1911.
    Rudin # P-168
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As ex-President about to be nominated by the new Progressive Party Addressee: Lady Gregory Writer's location: New York, NY, 7/2/12; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Discusses his feelings as Progressive candidate in the 1912 presidential election. Included is a TLS (secretarially signed) dated 10/19/1912. From the hospital, Roosevelt mentions campaigning and the unsuccessful assassination attempt on his life.
    Rudin # P-169
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Office held: As ex-President Addressee: "Dr. Henry Waldo Coe, Senator from Oregon" Writer's location: New York, NY, 11/7/14; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    "The public at large had gotten tired of all of us reformers and especially of me".
    Rudin # P-170
  - Taft, William H. Office held: As President Writer's location:, 8/22/11; Pages: 24 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Archive consisting of two drafts of Taft's "Special Message of the President of the United States, Returning Without Approval House Bill No. 12812. An Act to reduce the duties on Manufacture of Cotton".
    Rudin # P-171
  - Taft, William H. Addressee: Walter Smith Writer's location: Washington, DC., 11/9/12; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Taft discusses his loss to Woodrow Wilson in the 1912 election.
  - Taft, William H. Office held: "As ex-President and Professor of Law, Yale University" Addressee: S.G. Bayne Writer's location: New Haven, CT, 9/20/13; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Discusses losing some of his weight.
    Rudin # P-172
  - Taft, William H. Office held: As ex-President and Joint Chairman of the National War Labor Board Addressee: "Clarence H. Kelsey, President, Title Guarantee and Trust Co." Writer's location: Pointe-au-Pic, Quebec, Canada, 8/4/18; Pages: 1 1/2 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Sees a long war continuing, discusses Russia and Germany, calls for a larger American draft.
    Rudin # P-173
  - Taft, William H. Office held: "As ex-President and Professor of Law, Yale University" Addressee: "Dudley E. Waters, President Grand Rapids Bank" Writer's location: New Haven, CT, 11/17/19; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Discusses sound education and the formation of educational funds.
    Rudin # P-174
  - Taft, William H. Office held: As ex-President and Chief Justice of the United States Addressee: "Clarence H. Kelsey, President, Title Guarantee and Trust Co." Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 10/6/22; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Regarding his High Court colleagues.
    Rudin # P-175
  - Taft, William H. Office held: As ex-President and Chief Justice of the United States Addressee: Honorable Charles G. Washburn Writer's location: Pointe-au-Pic Quebec, Canada, 9/23/27; Pages: 2 1/2 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Acknowledges his 70th birthday; discusses what he would like to do in his remaining years.
    Rudin # P-176
  - Taylor, Zachary Office held: As Major General Writer's location:, During Mexican War; Pages: 1
    Part of a Pay Voucher including servants. See also Rudin #84 in the Gail and Stephen Rudin Slavery Collection, collection #4681.
    Rudin # P-177
  - Taylor, Zachary Office held: As Major General Addressee: Mr. S.C. Holden Writer's location: Camp near Monterray, Mexico, 1847-06-29; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Citizens of Batavia, NY endorse Taylor for President. He says that there are much better men than himself who are qualified. With newspaper article.
    Rudin # P-178
  - Truman, Harry, Stamps (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Envelope with stamps.
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Addressee: Senator Walter F. George Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 8/25/45; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Reviews troop redeployment at war's end.
    Rudin # P-179
  - Truman, Harry, 1848; Newspaper (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Chicago Daily Tribune of the election.
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Addressee: David H. Morgan Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 7/16/48; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Ridicules the hypocritical Republican platform.
    Rudin # P-180
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Writer's location: "Cabinet Room The White House Washington, D.C.", 8/12/48; Pages: 2 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Authorizing loan for construction of U.N. Headquarters in N.Y. City.
    Rudin # P-181
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Addressee: Wilbur J. Abell Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 4/4/50; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    "We have tried to arrange things so that (Margaret) would attain that success on merit".
    Rudin # P-182
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Addressee: "Barney Nover The Denver Post" Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 11/4/50; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    Refers to his attempted assassination.
    Rudin # P-183
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As President Addressee: Edward D. McKim Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 4/14/51; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    On the firing of MacArthur. From the Forbes Collection - Part Six.
    Rudin # P-184
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Paul V. Lutz Writer's location: Independence, Missouri, 6/22/59; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Former Presidents are discarded.
    Rudin # P-185
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Winston Norman Writer's location: Independence, Missouri, 1960-01; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Says "No" to running for President in 1960. Included is a copy of a letter from Norman to Truman (1/8/1950) asking him to accept the Presidential nomination. Envelope of Truman letter has a printed Free Frank signature.
    Rudin # P-186
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Honorable Leonor K. Sullivan Writer's location: Independence, Missouri, 10/5/60; Pages: 1 1/2 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    Vigorously campaigns for the Democratic Presidential ticket of John Kennedy and Lyndon Johnson.
    Rudin # P-187
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Robert Lovett Writer's location: Independence, Missouri, 8/5/70; Pages: 1 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    How a teacher should communicate with students. Envelope has printed Free Frank Signature.
    Rudin # P-189
  - Truman, Harry Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Miss. Maria Smith Writer's location: Independence, Missouri, 12/9/70; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Explains the "S" in his name. Envelope has printed Free Frank Signature.
    Rudin # P-190
  - Tyler, John Office held: As President Writer's location:, 1841-11-10; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 1A)
    Four Language Sea Letter for the Bark "Elizabeth" for a whaling voyage.
    Rudin # P-191
  - Tyler, John Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Robert Tyler (his son) Writer's location: Sherwood Forest, 1849-01-19; Pages: 1 1/2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Mourns the loss of his grandson to cholera.
    Rudin # P-192
  - Van Buren, Martin Office held: As Secretary of State Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1829-07-13; Pages: 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Certificate of Copyright for the book "Sketches of Naval Life".
    Rudin # P-193
  - Van Buren, Martin Office held: As Vice President Addressee: William C. Rives Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 1836-02-14; Pages: 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Reports on diplomatic affairs involving France and Great Britain.
    Rudin # P-194
  - Van Buren, Martin Office held: As ex-President Addressee: Henry D. Gilpin Writer's location: Lindenwald, 1856-06-10; Pages: 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Political letter on the 1856 Presidential Election, Van Buren's relationship with James Buchanan, and the Democratic Party's chances in New York State.
    Rudin # P-195
  - Washington, George, 1939, 1982; Stamps (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Commemorative stamps.
  - Washington, George Office held: As ex-Commander of the Continental Army Addressee: Colonel John Fitzpatrick Writer's location: Mount Vernon, 1785-11-26; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    The toil of a legislator re: the Potomac Company. Not in "Writings" ed. J.C. Fitzpatrick.
    Rudin # P-196
  - Wilson, Woodrow Office held: "As Professor of Law and Politics, Princeton University" Addressee: Frank Walter Brooks Writer's location: "Judd Haven, Ontario, Canada", 9/11/00; Pages: 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    On the Constitution as a living document. Included with this letter is correspondence regarding its possible sale to Thomas Madigan in 1936. Madigan was a well known autograph dealer of his day who wrote a book titled "Word Shadows of the Great".
    Rudin # P-197
  - Wilson, Woodrow Office held: As President Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 1916-03; Pages: 2 1/2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    In the wake of Pershing's pursuit of Pancho Villa, Wilson tries to manage the press. From the Forbes Collection - Part One.
    Rudin # P-198
  - Wilson, Woodrow Office held: As President Writer's location: "The White House Washington, D.C.", 1/29/17; Pages: 3 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Vote of the Immigration Bill. H.R. 10384.
    Rudin # P-199
  - Wilson, Woodrow Office held: As President Addressee: "Clarence Dillon, War Industries Board " Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 9/6/19; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    First "dollar a year men" check. Countersigned by Bernard Baruch.
    Rudin # P-200
  - Wilson, Woodrow Office held: As ex-President Addressee: "Eleanor Wilson McAdoo (Wilson's Daughter)" Writer's location: Washington, D.C., 12/18/22; Pages: 1 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    "In spite of breakdown and political persecution, I realize that I am the most fortunate man in the world".
    Rudin # P-201
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Signed Books
Keeping Faith: Memoirs of a President, by Jimmy Carter, 1982.
A Time to Heal, by Gerald Ford, 1979.
No More Vietnams, by Richard Nixon. 2 copies, one unsigned.
The Audacity of Hope, by Barack Obama.
Report of the Commissioner of Patents for the year 1849, Office of Printers to the Senate. Contains patent listing for Abraham Lincoln.